OK, um, welcome to week 6 of cybersecurity management.
NOTE CONF
This week we're talking about risk management.
This is an upload-only lecture, uh, recording because I was
NOTE CONF
not able to make it to the campus due to
a foot injury.
NOTE CONF
Um, my apologies for that.
Uh, hopefully, next week we'll be back to our regular
NOTE CONF
program of face to face lectures.
So, Let's begin.
NOTE CONF
So this week, we're studying uh risk management.
Um, as always, you're going to have your canvas module,
NOTE CONF
which is going to cover the material that I'm going
to be talking about uh in more detail.
NOTE CONF
There is a textbook, 121 to 175, approximately 40, 50
pages, yes.
NOTE CONF
Again, a lot of reading for risk management, mainly because
the textbook goes into a lot of detail explaining the
NOTE CONF
precise process.
And it is very helpful.
NOTE CONF
I'm going to try to go into detail as well.
And as I said last week, um, The textbook is
NOTE CONF
there to support your understanding.
So whatever I do not, uh, whatever you don't understand
NOTE CONF
from what I'm saying, you can go to the textbook
and look for more detail or more understanding, but we
NOTE CONF
certainly won't be examining you on material that is in
the textbook but is not covered in this presentation or
NOTE CONF
referenced in this presentation.
Uh, answer discussion questions on Canvas, chat with your peers
NOTE CONF
there, attend the workshop, of course, and after this, uh,
well, after the, uh, Tuesday slot, you can continue to,
NOTE CONF
um, discuss with your peers throughout the week.
In this week's workshop, uh, we are going to have
NOTE CONF
a quiz.
Uh, this is the 2nd of your 5 quizzes.
NOTE CONF
Uh, for most of the workshops running this week, there
will be more presentations.
NOTE CONF
This is the 2nd and hopefully last week of presentations.
Uh, for perhaps 1 class, there won't be presentations covering
NOTE CONF
the entire, uh, slot.
So look to your tutor for activities, um, for the
NOTE CONF
rest of the 2 hours.
If there is time, there will be a Q&A session
NOTE CONF
on this week's material, and if there is time, there
will be a teaching case, uh, the Horizon teaching case
NOTE CONF
will be discussed.
Uh, I believe there will be, uh, you need to
NOTE CONF
catch up on previous scenes from that story.
This week's learning objectives are to understand the purpose, uh,
NOTE CONF
role, and real-world drivers for information security management, the process,
and identify the key phases.
NOTE CONF
So, uh, we're now gonna talk about how you do
risk management, what is the process, and what are the
NOTE CONF
key deficiencies or key issues with the way that security
risk management is practiced in organizations.
NOTE CONF
So let's go back to the triplet model, our favorite
place to start.
NOTE CONF
As you know, a security problem really has to have
two aspects to it for there to be a viable
NOTE CONF
security problem.
You have to have something that's worth protecting, which is
NOTE CONF
an asset, and you have to have a danger to
that asset, otherwise known as a threat.
NOTE CONF
And as we said, as we have been saying every
week, the risk exposure that an organization has in totality
NOTE CONF
collectively is all the scenarios where a particular specific asset
is threatened by a specific threat.
NOTE CONF
In a sense there's a specific threat actor that is
exploiting a specific vulnerability to be able to impact that
NOTE CONF
asset.
And create a loss in value of some sort.
NOTE CONF
And as we have said again repeatedly, an organization is
likely to have quite a few assets, and there are
NOTE CONF
likely to be a lot of scenarios where where that
asset could be impacted, and each scenario is a risk
NOTE CONF
that has to be identified, enumerated, and Considered for some
kind of control and ultimately security management then becomes the
NOTE CONF
ability to control the portfolio of risks that an organization
is exposed to by leveraging its budget, its personnel, its.
NOTE CONF
Administrative managerial technological controls to its best advantage and the,
the target here, the um outcome that we are looking
NOTE CONF
for is the balance, the balance between the resources that
we have to spend on security and the amount of
NOTE CONF
exposure that we can reduce to control our situation, right?
That's what we're trying to get to.
NOTE CONF
So in this week, we're gonna talk about.
How we actually do the risk management bit, right, which
NOTE CONF
is how do we approach the task of identifying these
scenarios and assessing them and then deciding on what approach
NOTE CONF
to take to control them and so forth.
So, in a big picture, the overview here is.
NOTE CONF
That risk management has 3 main phases to it identification,
assessment, and control.
NOTE CONF
In the bigger picture, identification is fundamentally about.
Um Figuring out first, what is the scope of the
NOTE CONF
problem that we are trying to address here.
If we're trying to identify risks, it's risks about what?
NOTE CONF
And you can, you can imagine if you were doing
a risk assessment in your departmental unit, it could be
NOTE CONF
the scope could be just the risks that apply to
this unit, or it could be the risks that apply
NOTE CONF
to my department, or it could be risks that apply
to my organization, or it could be risks that apply
NOTE CONF
to the ecosystem within which my organization operates.
So, as you can see in each of these cases,
NOTE CONF
the pool of risks that you're going to identify is
going to be different.
NOTE CONF
And so knowing what the right scope is, is critical.
You don't want to start off with just trying to
NOTE CONF
identify randomly whatever risks occur to you to find out
later that you've been focusing or spending a lot of
NOTE CONF
energy identifying and worrying about risks that are not your
problem, or conversely, that you have confidently identified certain risks
NOTE CONF
and, and omitted others that also are your problem, um,
but they were never in scope.
NOTE CONF
So it's important to get the context establishment right.
And then what are the assets that we're trying to
NOTE CONF
protect?
Without knowing what the assets are, we certainly can't know
NOTE CONF
what the scenarios are.
Then, not just identifying the assets, but valuing these assets,
NOTE CONF
because if you have a lot of assets and you
start your risk management process, you certainly don't want to
NOTE CONF
start with the least important or least valued assets.
You want to start with the most valued assets to
NOTE CONF
save on time, to be efficient.
And then, how do I develop scenarios?
NOTE CONF
If I know what the asset is, and I know
what the, you know, threat actors are that are operating
NOTE CONF
my space, how do I come up with these scenarios?
That's the, these are the, the questions that we ask
NOTE CONF
for risk identification.
For risk assessment, once we have the scenarios from the
NOTE CONF
identification phase, we need to ask the question, well, How
do we work out the risk, right?
NOTE CONF
So we've got a risk scenario, but what is the
risk coming from the scenario?
NOTE CONF
And here we'll we'll explain that risk is probability times
impact.
NOTE CONF
So we need to know these two factors in order
to calculate the risk, which is what is the likelihood
NOTE CONF
that this scenario is going to happen and what is
the impact if it does happen.
NOTE CONF
And once we have these two factors, we can assign
them numbers based on some yardstick.
NOTE CONF
And that yardstick will help us to determine what is
the.
NOTE CONF
Highest likelihood, highest consequence.
As opposed to lowest likelihood, lowest consequence, if we can
NOTE CONF
in that way, once we have a yardstick, we can
start prioritizing these and then come up with a, a
NOTE CONF
mega list.
That will have the highest criticality or highest risk at
NOTE CONF
the top and the lowest at the bottom.
And that would conclude the risk assessment phase, and then
NOTE CONF
we've got risk control, which is, OK, now that we've
got our sorted list of risk scenarios, what is our
NOTE CONF
approach to controlling this portfolio of risks, and what tools
do we have at our disposal to control these risks?
NOTE CONF
And how can we apply these tools.
We won't spend so much time on the control side
NOTE CONF
of things, other than to give you a satisfactory ending
to this long process of identifying risks to controlling risks.
NOTE CONF
So let's talk about risk identification.
Um, The first step, as I said, was to establish
NOTE CONF
context and As I also said, there are different ways,
different scopes, and it really makes a big difference what
NOTE CONF
your scope is.
Here's some of the considerations that you would, you would
NOTE CONF
look at when you're trying to establish what is the
scope of my risk, you know, problem.
NOTE CONF
Um, and one is, what are the, who are the
external partners and who are the internal partners or stakeholders
NOTE CONF
that I have to be concerned about.
So, suppliers, customers, regulators.
NOTE CONF
And, you know, internal finance, you know, HR, all of
these different parties that constitute the ecosystem within which my
NOTE CONF
organization operates, um, they all have, they're all a source
of risk, right?
NOTE CONF
So, for instance, a, um, supplier sends you.
You know, materials that are substandard and that substandard material,
NOTE CONF
well, let's say they're providing electronic parts and you put
that into your operating environment and it sabotages your environment.
NOTE CONF
Well, you've just, you know, created a cyber risk and
that has the source of that is your supplier.
NOTE CONF
So it's an example of how it's important that your
context establishment covers.
NOTE CONF
You know, um, upstream and downstream risk.
Um, identify assets well.
NOTE CONF
So for identify assets, you will need to do a
big inventory um of all the different assets in your
NOTE CONF
company and you'll have to come up with a definition
of what's an asset.
NOTE CONF
And in many cases, this is easy, right?
So for example, every digital platform that plays a significant
NOTE CONF
role in your company, whether it be email or a
database or a customer relationship management system, a CRM or
NOTE CONF
any IT service.
Uh, that's important to your firm, e-commerce service, you know,
NOTE CONF
web, website, etc.
These are all digital platforms, they're all assets.
NOTE CONF
And this is actually easy to do, right, because digital
platforms are easy to enumerate.
NOTE CONF
But sensitive data, there are, there's a lot of sensitive
data in your organization.
NOTE CONF
How are we going to figure out and make an
inventory of all the sensitive data?
NOTE CONF
And there's a bit of a trick to it.
So I remember when I did this, I was, I
NOTE CONF
was working as a consultant some 20 years ago, and
one of the big projects that I was doing pretty
NOTE CONF
much on my own was to identify.
To do a risk assessment of the information resources of
NOTE CONF
a.
Um, a multinational company that was headquartered here in Melbourne.
NOTE CONF
And I basically started with an organization chart and I
asked the question, OK, for every department, I'm going to
NOTE CONF
go to every department's head and I'm going to sit
with them and say, what information do you have in
NOTE CONF
your department?
Do you use to be able to do your job?
NOTE CONF
Let's make a list.
And together we would make a long list of all
NOTE CONF
the different information assets, and we'd go through motion by
motion what they do.
NOTE CONF
Right?
So, what are the types of things that you output?
NOTE CONF
What's your input?
Where does, you know, where does the information come from?
NOTE CONF
Um, what are your processes and what information do they
use?
NOTE CONF
How many people exist, what's, what's their job, and so
forth.
NOTE CONF
And we would just keep on, I just keep on
querying until the, the Head of the department, say, yep,
NOTE CONF
this pretty much sums up all the information that we
have.
NOTE CONF
And from that, I'd come up with an inventory and
where I'd have to, I'd cluster documents together to say,
NOTE CONF
OK, this is all documents that work together are essentially
the same thing, they're just copies of each other, etc.
NOTE CONF
etc.
um, and that would be my, my big inventory.
NOTE CONF
Um, capabilities is a lot harder, so capability, uh, in
the sense that it's harder to identify, but there's less
NOTE CONF
of that.
So, asking the organization, what is your key capability and
NOTE CONF
then figuring out how that capability is broken down into
people's process technology integrations, that's something you'll need to do.
NOTE CONF
And so, once we've done all of this, we need
to value assets, right?
NOTE CONF
Which is to figure out what, how do we put
a dollar value to an asset to be able to
NOTE CONF
value it, right?
Um, now, we'll come to the details of how to
NOTE CONF
do the valuation in a moment, but here's an example
of all the different types of information.
NOTE CONF
Excuse me, all the different types of information assets that
you might have, right?
NOTE CONF
So, if you look at IT operations, you've got passwords,
you've got cert digital certificates, you've got security tokens, you've
NOTE CONF
got biometrics, a huge amount of information.
You've got systems and data, then in hardware configurations.
NOTE CONF
Business operations information, customer information, financial information, intellectual property information
like trademarks and copyrights and R&D data, employee information, and
NOTE CONF
there's more.
There's confidential information of, uh, from your legal, you know,
NOTE CONF
team, uh, the advice that they give you, the contracts
that you signed, litigation documents, non-disclosure agreements, uh, internal investigations,
NOTE CONF
whistleblower complaints.
And then there's regulatory compliance information, audit reports, etc.
NOTE CONF
There's employee records, um, internal employee records, the salaries of
your employees if you're a private company can be hugely,
NOTE CONF
you know, sensitive, unlike in a public organization where everybody
knows what, what everybody makes.
NOTE CONF
In a private organization, it's quite possible that, you know,
a supervisor earns less than a, an employee, an employee
NOTE CONF
they supervise, but they don't know it.
Um, and recruitment information, people's CVs, maybe people's, you know,
NOTE CONF
medical records that were queried at the recruitment time.
And then physical security information like, you know, CCTV camera
NOTE CONF
information and third-party contracts, you know, service-level agreements with other
parties, etc.
NOTE CONF
etc.
and what you're paying, you know, these, these contractors to
NOTE CONF
do particular work.
So there is a lot of information out there that's
NOTE CONF
at different levels of value that need to be inventoried
in order to be assessed.
NOTE CONF
So, an example of how you might um create an
inventory, I've already discussed like how you go from, you
NOTE CONF
know, one part of the organization to another part to
find the information assets.
NOTE CONF
But once you have like a, an, a list of
information assets which you can see here on the left-hand
NOTE CONF
side, you want to um figure out what is the
impact of to profitability if something happened to this asset.
NOTE CONF
And, you know, that is an important way to value
your asset.
NOTE CONF
The data classification bit is a sensitivity analysis, which we
are not really covering this week, but you do, you
NOTE CONF
would probably have a classification protocol, what is confidential, what
is public, what is private, etc.
NOTE CONF
and definitions in your organization about what constitutes.
Um, uh, this category, and then you would apply it
NOTE CONF
across the board, and that would, you know, be listed
here as well.
NOTE CONF
But from an impact of profitability, you would have on
your right-hand side, all of these.
NOTE CONF
You know, ratings How do we get to that impact
to profitability figure?
NOTE CONF
Well, we probably will decide that impact to profitability has
multiple criteria, right?
NOTE CONF
Impact to revenue might be one.
It's all right, let me just go back.
NOTE CONF
Um, sorry, um, impact in general will have multiple criteria.
Impact revenue, impact to profitability, public image impact, etc.
NOTE CONF
etc.
and you'd have to go to different people to figure
NOTE CONF
out what these figures mean.
So for example, the person who actually owns this do
NOTE CONF
these documents and uses it on a day to day
basis can only qualitatively describe what would happen if they
NOTE CONF
lost the document.
They can't describe at an organizational level what would be
NOTE CONF
the impact to revenue.
They would say, hey, if I lost this document, I
NOTE CONF
wouldn't be able to do A, B, and Z.
This process would stop.
NOTE CONF
This would be the impact qualitatively, right?
And they can describe the crisis situation, right?
NOTE CONF
Um, at an operations level, but you eventually have to
go to the to the CFO, right?
NOTE CONF
And ask the CFO, well, you know, the whole organization,
what it's worth, it's, you know, productivity, blah, blah, blah,
NOTE CONF
uh, what it's operating budget is.
So tell me, if this happened, what percent, what, what,
NOTE CONF
how would you value this or, you know, what would
be the impact, um, in a dollar sense?
NOTE CONF
And they would, they would give you.
That figure, right?
NOTE CONF
What looks to be like a crisis at an operations
level might be, you know, meh, nothing major at a
NOTE CONF
strategic level.
So, these numbers here, 30, 40, 30 are basically awaiting.
NOTE CONF
You're basically saying, This is a weighted factor analysis worksheet,
which says of the total impact, right?
NOTE CONF
We're gonna derive the impact rating from 3 sub-ratings, impact
revenue, impact of profitability, impact from public image or impact
NOTE CONF
from reputation.
And we're going to We are going to weight impact
NOTE CONF
revenues 30% of the overall impact, profitability 40%, and reputation
or public image 30%, so these add to 100%.
NOTE CONF
Then we are going to work out what the individual
ratings are for each of these columns, and we are
NOTE CONF
going to multiply, you know, these by the weighting and
come to a total impact score, which is a weighted
NOTE CONF
score.
And this way, if we decide suddenly that revenue matters
NOTE CONF
more than profitability, we can change these ratings.
This will not change, right?
NOTE CONF
But the Overall impact the way the organization looks at
it will change.
NOTE CONF
Right?
That is important because it then allows us to correctly
NOTE CONF
weight the value of assets.
OK, once we have valued assets, we can now go
NOTE CONF
to.
Assess to the probability assessment.
NOTE CONF
How do we figure out the likelihood of a scenario?
The way I used to do it was to simply
NOTE CONF
interview people who handle the document and to say, you
know, Well, you know, how often has this document been,
NOTE CONF
you know, leaked to your knowledge, right?
Once a week, once a month, once 6 months, once
NOTE CONF
in a year.
And I asked the same question to everybody, right?
NOTE CONF
The important thing with likelihood scaling is that you have
to ask everybody the same question and use the same
NOTE CONF
yardstick.
You can't switch yardsticks or all the likelihoods will be
NOTE CONF
wrong, right?
So you basically decide high probability might be once a
NOTE CONF
week, low probability might be once a year, medium probability
might be once, I don't know, in 6 months.
NOTE CONF
You can decide as long as you use a consistent.
Yardstick, you will be able to do your risk assessment
NOTE CONF
because it is a it is a relative rating.
Um, where can I get likelihood information from?
NOTE CONF
You could also, you can interview people, which is what
I did when I didn't have time, but you could
NOTE CONF
look up past records.
You could look up, um, you could do a simulation.
NOTE CONF
You could experiment, you could try things out.
You could get an external expert to come in and
NOTE CONF
say, well, I've worked in organizations for a long time
using this kind of information, and I know that, you
NOTE CONF
know, that these documents disappear every, you know, 1 week
or something, not every 6 months like they're saying.
NOTE CONF
So, again, lots of different sources from which you can
derive your likelihoods.
NOTE CONF
Impact Um, So the impact can come from direct cost,
right?
NOTE CONF
If this document gets destroyed, how much will it cost
to recreate?
NOTE CONF
Could be, you know, how many hours of time will
it take you to be able to recreate this.
NOTE CONF
Uh, if we breach, you know, if this is, if
this document happens to be a confidential document and by
NOTE CONF
losing it or destroying it, we are in breach of
a contract, how much is the penalty, right?
NOTE CONF
So all of these are ways to figure out what
the cost of um a risk scenario might be.
NOTE CONF
Ultimately, when you have A, uh, the probability rating, which
we can say is low, medium, high, and, Impact rating,
NOTE CONF
which is low, medium, high.
So, as I said before, we say low in probability
NOTE CONF
might be once a year, high might be.
Um, once a week, and media might be every 6
NOTE CONF
months.
For A dollar value, we can decide on impact what
NOTE CONF
low, medium, and high is by making dollar ranges.
But now, how do we calculate the risk?
NOTE CONF
Well, we can say low is a 1, medium is
a 2, and high is a 3 for likelihood.
NOTE CONF
And then similarly for impact, we can say low is
a 1, medium is a 2, and high impact is
NOTE CONF
a 3.
And so we just multiply these out.
NOTE CONF
So the criticality rating of a scenario is the probability
times the impact.
NOTE CONF
So a high criticality scenario will have high probability, high
impact, and so that will rate a 9.
NOTE CONF
A low criticality will be low probability, low impact, which
will be rated a 1.
NOTE CONF
So 1 times 1 is 1.
And now that you've got a rating number for each
NOTE CONF
scenario, you can simply sort the 9s go to the
top, the 1s go to the bottom, and everything else
NOTE CONF
comes in between.
And we now have a Sorted, prioritized list of scenarios.
NOTE CONF
The most important ones that we need to pay attention
to are at the top, and the least important ones
NOTE CONF
are at the bottom.
You could also use a grid like this one, where
NOTE CONF
you, and, and here in this grid, we've got 12345
different ratings for likelihood and 12345 different ratings for severity.
NOTE CONF
And if I hit play here, you can see, right,
low, medium, medium to high, it's medium high and then
NOTE CONF
high.
These are the different.
NOTE CONF
Uh, you know, ratings that a particular scenario can have.
And these would be your sort of, you know, 1s
NOTE CONF
and 2s and so forth, 1s and 2s and maybe
3s, and then your, if you're doing uh 12, sorry,
NOTE CONF
5 by 5, that's your highest will be 25, these
will be 25s and 24s maybe, right?
NOTE CONF
So, this kind of grid helps you to imagine, the
greater the If the risk scenario is positioned towards the
NOTE CONF
top right, it's higher, if it's towards the bottom left,
it's lower.
NOTE CONF
Right.
OK, once we have done that, once we have prioritized
NOTE CONF
our risk scenarios, and we have a long list, and
we know exactly what's the most critical and what's the
NOTE CONF
least critical, we now need to decide how are we
going to control this list of scenarios.
NOTE CONF
And that's pretty, you know, that's also pretty uh challenging.
One thing we should do, which is not on this
NOTE CONF
list here, is we should probably decide what our risk
appetite is.
NOTE CONF
So if you've got risks rated from 1 to 9,
for instance, you're using only 3 ratings for likelihood, 3
NOTE CONF
ratings for impact, and you've got risks rated from 1
to 9.
NOTE CONF
If that is the case, then you can decide that
you're going to address and do something about every every
NOTE CONF
risk that's rated above a 4.
And you're simply not going to do anything that's below
NOTE CONF
a 4.
And that's called, you know, deciding on your risk appetite.
NOTE CONF
Right, that is something that you'll probably need to do
at some stage.
NOTE CONF
But in terms of risk control strategies, what can we
do about a risk?
NOTE CONF
We can.
Put in, we can transfer the risk, we can take
NOTE CONF
out insurance on a scenario, say if this happens, insurance
will cover it.
NOTE CONF
That's one possibility.
We can avoid the risk by re-engineering.
NOTE CONF
The scenario.
So for example, if the risk is, hey, somebody can
NOTE CONF
send us an.
You know, somebody can send us an SMS that will,
NOTE CONF
um, you know, trigger something really bad in a, in
a system of sorts, right?
NOTE CONF
We can just say, look, don't use SMS, use email.
Right?
NOTE CONF
And that swaps one risk scenario for another risk scenario,
but you can certainly avoid one risk scenario by simply
NOTE CONF
saying, we're not gonna use SMS for this type of,
you know, um, process, and by doing that, you basically
NOTE CONF
have completely negated every risk that comes natively from the
SMS service, right?
NOTE CONF
So, and then the other thing you can do is
you can also put in, let's say for example, a,
NOTE CONF
a fire, you know, like a, a mechanism that simply
avoids that, for example, somebody um can go through my
NOTE CONF
firewall and move from one subnet to another subnet, I
can say, well, how about we, we only want traffic
NOTE CONF
to be going in one direction because of the nature
of the subnets.
NOTE CONF
Why allow traffic to come back the other way when
that, we don't need that to happen.
NOTE CONF
So let's put a, a diode.
In the electrical circuitry that only allows traffic hardwired to
NOTE CONF
go in one way, right?
So by doing that, it's impossible for traffic to go
NOTE CONF
backwards.
Because it's electrically now hardwired into the network, the traffic
NOTE CONF
can only flow one way, so that's me avoiding that
risk scenario.
NOTE CONF
Mitigation is when the scenario, the risk scenario that you're
concerned about has happened, and then you do something after
NOTE CONF
the scenario to try to reduce the impact.
And an instant response team is a classic example, right?
NOTE CONF
Some attacker has gone through your firewalls, they've broken through
your shield, they're inside your organization, and now you've got
NOTE CONF
an instant response team whose job it is to find
them and to cut them out of the organization.
NOTE CONF
Um, acceptance is simply saying I'm not gonna do anything,
right?
NOTE CONF
If it happens, it happens, right?
So here's a really interesting um.
NOTE CONF
It's called, it's a, it's a methodology of risk assessment
called Octave.
NOTE CONF
Octave is actually a full-blown, very complex one.
This is Octave S, which is a very shortened view
NOTE CONF
of it.
And it's from Carnegie Mellon University.
NOTE CONF
They pioneered this and created it.
And I found it very useful because it sort of
NOTE CONF
gives you a really good idea of how all these
risk scenarios collectively um can be identified and then, and
NOTE CONF
then controlled.
So on your left hand side, you have the asset.
NOTE CONF
This is the customer relationship management system or CRM system.
And We say, for instance, that, hey, if somebody were
NOTE CONF
to attack the asset, they'd come through the network, they
could be an insider or an outsider.
NOTE CONF
The insider could be, you know, have an accidental motivation
or a deliberate motivation, and the outcome of that scenario
NOTE CONF
could be that information was disclosed or it was modified
or it was destroyed or it was temporarily just interrupted.
NOTE CONF
And the same four scenarios for each of that, of
each of those types of.
NOTE CONF
Scenarios.
So basically, every pathway is another risk scenario.
NOTE CONF
The dotted lines are the ones that in, for instance,
are considered to be not possible in that scenario.
NOTE CONF
So everything that's read is a legitimate validated possibility.
And so you can just count 123456789, 1011, 1213 different
NOTE CONF
scenarios have been validated as possible and for this particular
CRM system, right?
NOTE CONF
So, yeah, each pathway, another scenario.
Now, We've identified all the scenarios for this high-value asset.
NOTE CONF
We've already determined that it's high value, right?
Now, the question that we wanna pursue here is, what
NOTE CONF
is the risk to the organization of each scenario?
And the impact and the probability you can see in
NOTE CONF
these columns.
Impact has been, um, has 123456 contributing factors.
NOTE CONF
So, here, you'll see there's reputation, there's financial, there's productivity,
there's fines, there's safety, and there's other.
NOTE CONF
And what they've done here, what you can do here
if you're using this kind of method is you can
NOTE CONF
decide if each scenario, for each scenario, whether the reputation
is low, medium, high, the financial is low, medium, high,
NOTE CONF
productivity is low, medium, high, blah blah, and you obviously
have, you know, a categorization of what constitutes low, what
NOTE CONF
constitutes medium, what constitutes high for each one of these.
So, filling out all of this.
NOTE CONF
Right, so obviously you've only filled out where there's where
the reds.
NOTE CONF
You know, are solid lines.
Filling out all of this, in some cases, you might
NOTE CONF
say there where there's dashes that they don't apply, um,
you can now determine what the impact is collectively.
NOTE CONF
Right, from that.
Now, in terms of probability, there are 2.
NOTE CONF
Different subcolumns here.
There is low, medium, high, which is obviously a mark
NOTE CONF
of frequency.
Is it very likely to, is it high likely to
NOTE CONF
happen or not so likely to happen?
But there's this interesting confidence bar here, which basically says,
NOTE CONF
yeah, I've put medium, but how confident am I that
this medium likelihood is actually true.
NOTE CONF
And so if you're not at all, you put an
X there, and if you're very confident, you put an
NOTE CONF
X on this side, and this is a really neat
way of trying to record here, what your gut feel
NOTE CONF
was, because with likelihood, it is usually the least, Anchored
in the least likely to be anchored in a metric
NOTE CONF
of any kind, it's usually just gut feel, so you
want to record that gut feel somewhere in your sheet.
NOTE CONF
OK.
Now that you've identified each scenario, you've assessed the impact,
NOTE CONF
you've assessed the probability, the question now then becomes, What
do we do about something, right?
NOTE CONF
And you can see here now, this is the result
of an audit of all the different practice areas of
NOTE CONF
your security, you know, in across the organization.
So it covers security training to contingency planning, to physical
NOTE CONF
access control, blah, blah blah.
All of these, right, are legitimate practice areas.
NOTE CONF
And REDD is where you've done an audit according to
some international standard, and you've decided that this practice area
NOTE CONF
is weak.
And yellow is where it's, you know, sort of in
NOTE CONF
the middle.
It's got some weak points, some strong points, and green
NOTE CONF
is where you are fully compliant or you feel like
you are very strong on that, right?
NOTE CONF
And so, for each scenario, you can then decide, look,
what am I gonna do?
NOTE CONF
Am I gonna accept the risk?
Am I going to mitigate the risk, or am I
NOTE CONF
gonna defer?
Defer just means that I haven't made a decision yet,
NOTE CONF
I'll come back to it later.
But where, for instance, the organization has said, hey, we're
NOTE CONF
going to mitigate, we're going to do something to mitigate
the risk, they've actually circled what that mitigation means.
NOTE CONF
It means that we're going to invest in numbers 12
and 13, which is vulnerability management and encryption and security
NOTE CONF
policy and regulation, right?
That's what mitigation means for us.
NOTE CONF
Right?
Similarly here, mitigation here means we're gonna do contingency planning,
NOTE CONF
and we're going to do, um, again, vulnerability management and
encryption.
NOTE CONF
Right?
So now you see a whole on one page risk
NOTE CONF
assessment for the CRM system, from what scenarios we're concerned
about to what is the impact if they happened to
NOTE CONF
the likelihood of that happening, to the risk approach of
the organization, to what we're going to do about the
NOTE CONF
risk.
What does that approach actually mean?
NOTE CONF
So, in terms of deficiencies, um, There are some very
significant issues with the way that um.
NOTE CONF
But it's Sorry, continuing.
So, there are 3 possible deficiencies, right?
NOTE CONF
Uh Deficiency one is information security risk identification is common
perfunctory.
NOTE CONF
So what that means here is that when we do
risk when we come up with risk scenarios, we come
NOTE CONF
up with separate individual scenarios and we assess the likelihood
and impact separate to each scenario.
NOTE CONF
So we have like 100 scenarios, it's like 100 snapshots.
Of what might happen, and then we, we individually look
NOTE CONF
at each snapshot and decide, what is the risk that
that might happen and then put in a control or
NOTE CONF
something or avoid it or put in a plan to
manage it.
NOTE CONF
Now, in the real world.
Risks don't occur independent of each other, they actually combine,
NOTE CONF
right?
So my favorite example, it comes from aviation.
NOTE CONF
If, so if, for instance, in aviation, risk, risk management
and risk assessment is much more sophisticated.
NOTE CONF
If you've got an airplane sitting on the tarmac, and
there is a bolt that has fallen off the wing
NOTE CONF
of the airplane and is on the floor.
They're not just going to pick up the bolt and
NOTE CONF
put the bolt back into the wing and say, oh,
there was a risk that the bolt could fall, and,
NOTE CONF
you know, what is the likelihood and impact of that
happening, and we will put in a plan to make
NOTE CONF
sure that that part of the wing, if a bolt
falls, is not going to be affected.
NOTE CONF
What they will do is they'll say, oh, if a
bolt falls, and what if this was in the middle
NOTE CONF
of the air?
What would the change in forces be on the entire
NOTE CONF
aircraft?
Would it require, would it be likely that another bolt
NOTE CONF
would fall, and then another bolt and another bolt, like,
what is the combinatorial impact of one risk happening on
NOTE CONF
other things in the airplane?
So the likelihood of one risk happening changes the likelihood
NOTE CONF
of other risks happening.
And that is what the real world is like.
NOTE CONF
It's a snowball effect.
And so, we don't normally deal with that kind of
NOTE CONF
scenario because our modeling capability is very primitive.
We pretend that each scenario happens separately, and that is
NOTE CONF
a problem in the real organization, right?
And I think it's particularly problematic because risks, when we,
NOTE CONF
our risk assessments look like they're all happening because of
natural hazards, you know, lightning, fire, you know, flood.
NOTE CONF
But actually when somebody's attacking you, they are actually deliberately
going after every vulnerability that they can find, and that
NOTE CONF
means if one vulnerability is being exploited and there are
others, the attacker's going to go after those as well.
NOTE CONF
So it looks more like the snowballing effect than it
does the natural, you know, the natural hazard effect, but
NOTE CONF
we don't deal with that.
The second deficiency is uh Information security risks are commonly
NOTE CONF
estimated with little reference to the organization's actual situation.
So for example, you know, you ask somebody whose job
NOTE CONF
it is to, to come up with scenarios of risk
to say, oh, is this likely to happen?
NOTE CONF
What scenarios might happen with this asset, but.
What happens frequently is somebody will say, oh, nothing's gonna
NOTE CONF
happen to this asset, it's never been an issue, right?
But the instant response team that is logging all the
NOTE CONF
things that they're seeing on the network are seeing that
that issue, that the person who manages that information or
NOTE CONF
the owner of the assets that never happened, is happening
all the time, right?
NOTE CONF
So, because security management teams, you know, the, the risk
assessment teams and the instant response team rarely talk to
NOTE CONF
each other, it's very common for risk assessors to say,
oh, this won't happen, and then instant responders say, oh,
NOTE CONF
it happens all the time, right?
So that, what is actually going on in the organization
NOTE CONF
can be a matter of dispute, and that then shows
itself or manifests itself in your risk assessment.
NOTE CONF
Deficiency 3 information security risk assessment is not done, you
know, is not done.
NOTE CONF
Consistently and periodically, uh, rout so I should say routinely,
right?
NOTE CONF
It's done intermittently on a non-historical basis.
So it may happen once a year.
NOTE CONF
Right?
Maybe it happened once in 6 months if you're lucky,
NOTE CONF
but risks are changing every day.
So One of the reasons why risks aren't risk assessments
NOTE CONF
aren't being done very frequently is because of the expense
of it, right?
NOTE CONF
It's really expensive to do this big assessment.
Now, this is not to say that there is a
NOTE CONF
live risk register and people are recording risks as they're
going, but my point here is that taking the holistic
NOTE CONF
big picture of the organization, understanding what the risk, what
the, you know, what are the, what is the risk
NOTE CONF
context and going through this whole.
You know, sort of comprehensive risk review doesn't happen very
NOTE CONF
often because it's really expensive.
So lastly, um, I've got this really interesting scenario here,
NOTE CONF
this really, um.
I love the story.
NOTE CONF
It's um from ancient China.
I think it is 3rd century BC.
NOTE CONF
Um And the story goes like this.
The lord of ancient China once asked his physician, who
NOTE CONF
is a member of a family of healers, which of
which of his family of healers was most skilled in
NOTE CONF
healing.
And he said, My eldest brother sees the spirit of
NOTE CONF
sickness and removes it before it takes shape.
So his name does not get out of the house.
NOTE CONF
My elder brother cures sickness when it is still extremely
minute, so his name does not get out of the
NOTE CONF
neighborhood.
As for me, I puncture veins, prescribe potions, and massage
NOTE CONF
skin.
So from time to time my name gets out and
NOTE CONF
is heard among the lords.
So there's 3 brothers here.
NOTE CONF
The eldest brother, who is such an expert healer that
he sees the spirit, the sickness as it is emerging
NOTE CONF
in its most minute state.
And removes it before it even has a chance.
NOTE CONF
His elder brother.
Is not as skilled, so the illness is is able
NOTE CONF
to take shape.
And he cures it at a much later stage than
NOTE CONF
the eldest brother.
As for the youngest brother, he is the one who
NOTE CONF
is the least skilled, so the illness takes hold of
the patient, and the younger brother goes to war, so
NOTE CONF
to speak, to try to save the person's life, and
it's an epic battle, and he obviously does, does succeed.
NOTE CONF
And when he does succeed, he becomes famous because people
are obviously saying, oh, this person's never gonna survive, blah
NOTE CONF
blah, and then he lives and he becomes famous.
Now, Which, there are two questions here.
NOTE CONF
Which of the brothers is most risk aware?
Right.
NOTE CONF
Which is least risk aware?
Right?
NOTE CONF
Who can see the scenario, the risk scenario at the
earliest stage?
NOTE CONF
And which is the least competent in seeing the risk
scenario.
NOTE CONF
Right, and I think If you need a second pause.
Pause the video, have a think about it.
NOTE CONF
And then we'll play it, and I'll tell you what
the answer is.
NOTE CONF
So the answer is The eldest brother is the most
risk aware and the and the youngest brother is the
NOTE CONF
least risk aware.
Right?
NOTE CONF
And the reason, of course, is because the eldest brother
is able to see the emergence of the Of the
NOTE CONF
sickness at its earliest stage, right?
Has the foresight to be able to tell that this
NOTE CONF
person is going to become sick, perhaps, right?
Because of the lifestyle or the diet or whatever, right?
NOTE CONF
Question 2.
Is, is a bit more tricky.
NOTE CONF
What's the key lesson that we learned from this story
from a security point of view?
NOTE CONF
Why is it that the youngest brother is the most
famous?
NOTE CONF
And the eldest brother is unknown.
Outside of the house.
NOTE CONF
How come?
Or in other words, who is the most accomplished or
NOTE CONF
most famous or most well-paid security or risk manager, let's
say, in these three brothers, right?
NOTE CONF
I think it's obvious that the most famous and most
well-paid risk manager is the youngest brother, not the eldest
NOTE CONF
brother.
So, what lesson do we derive from this?
NOTE CONF
Right?
Have a think about that.
NOTE CONF
How do you?
How do you, um.
NOTE CONF
How do you, um?
How do you justify this?
NOTE CONF
Well, the interesting thing here is the risk manager that
is most likely to be fired is the eldest brother.
NOTE CONF
Because Think about a security manager who is well paid,
but there's no crisis, there's no incident.
NOTE CONF
The organization's going to say, Well, why do we need
this person?
NOTE CONF
We're paying them to do nothing and they'll get fired.
Not realizing that the reason why nothing is happening is
NOTE CONF
because it's being dealt with at a very early stage.
So there's a bit of a paradox here, right?
NOTE CONF
The least competent risk manager is the most well paid.
The most competent is the least well paid and most
NOTE CONF
likely to be fired.
So what's the lesson?
NOTE CONF
And the lesson here is that not only do you
need to be doing good security risk management, you also
NOTE CONF
need to be seen to be doing good security risk
management, which means you have to convey.
NOTE CONF
To all the people around you, what you're doing to
make the organization secure so that they appreciate all the
NOTE CONF
effort you're putting into security and they can correlate that
effort with the stability or the lack of incidents that
NOTE CONF
are happening in the organization.
So that concludes uh today's presentation, and I thank you
NOTE CONF
for listening and I will see you next week.